Wil Thomason

CONTACT INFORMATION	Rice University 804.591.7318 Department of Computer Science wbthomason@rice.edu DH 3053, 6100 Main Street https://wbthomason.github.io
	Houston, TX 77005
CURRENT Position	Postdoctoral Research Associate, Rice University, Houston, TX Since January 2022
RESEARCH INTERESTS	Robotics, integrated task and motion planning, ML for planning, constrained planning, formal methods for robotics, synthesis, motion planning, multi-agent coordination
Awards	Computing Innovation Postdoctoral Fellowship Computing Research Association (CRA) and National Science Foundation (NSF) August 2021
	Outstanding Teaching Assistant Award Cornell University Department of Computer Science May 2017
	NDSEG Fellow April 2017 American Society for Engineering Education
	NSF GRFP Fellow March 2017 The National Science Foundation
	Outstanding Teaching Assistant Award Cornell University Department of Computer Science May 2016
	NSF GRFP Honorable Mention The National Science Foundation March 2016
	Louis T. Rader Outstanding Education Undergraduate Student University of Virginia Department of Computer Science May 2015
PEER-REVIEWED CONFERENCE PUBLICATIONS	 A Unified Sampling-Based Approach to Integrated Task and Motion Planning. Wil Thomason and Ross Knepper. ISRR 2019. Social Momentum: A Framework for Legible Navigation in Dynamic Multi-Agent Environments. Christoforos Mavrogiannis, Wil Thomason, Ross Knepper. HRI 2018. Zero-Shot Learning for Unfamiliar Gesture Recognition. Wil Thomason and Ross Knepper. ISER 2016.
Journal Publications	 Social Momentum: Design and Evaluation of a Framework for Socially Competent Robot Navigation. Christoforos Mavrogiannis, Patrícia Alves-Oliveira, Wil Thomason, Ross A. Knepper. T-HRI 2021. An Accurate Real-Time RFID-Based Location System. Kirti Chawla, Christopher McFarland, Gabriel Robins, Wil Thomason. International Journal of Radio Frequency Identification Technology and Applications. July 2016, authors listed in alphabetical order.
Preprints	 Counterexample-Guided Repair for Symbolic-Geometric Action Abstractions. Wil Thomason and Hadas Kress-Gazit. 2021. Ensuring Progress for Multiple Mobile Robots via Space Partitioning, Motion Rules, and Adaptively Centralized Conflict Resolution. Claire Liang*, Wil Thomason*, Elizabeth Ricci, and Soham Sankaran. 2021.
Workshop Presentations	"Robust, Efficient, and Flexible Robot Planning." July 11, 2020. RSS Pioneers 2020 "A Flexible Sampling-Based Approach to Task and Motion Planning." June 23, 2019. RSS 2019 Workshop on Robust Task and Motion Planning

"Which comes first, the task plan or the motion plan?." June 30, 2018. RSS 2018 Workshop on Exhibition and Benchmarking of Task and Motion Planners. Joint with Ross A. Knepper.

"Exploiting Heterogeneity in Robot Teams Through a Formalism of Capabilities." July 15, 2017. RSS 2018 Workshop on Heterogeneity and Diversity for Resilience in Multi-Robot Systems

"Toward Contextual Grounding of Unfamiliar Gestures for Human-Robot Interaction." May 30, 2017. FG 2017: First International Workshop on Adaptive Shot Learning for Gesture Understanding and Production

"Recognizing Unfamiliar Gestures for Human-Robot Interaction through Zero-Shot Learning." June 19th, 2016. 2nd Workshop on Model Learning for Human-Robot Communication, RSS 2016

INVITED TALKS AND CONSORTIA

Search Based Planning Lab

2020

Invited to present my work on integrated task and motion planning and automatic abstraction repair in the Search Based Planning Lab.

RSS Pioneers Workshop (virtual due to COVID-19)

2020

Selective annual workshop in conjunction with the Robotics: Science and Systems conference. Designed to "bring together a cohort of the world's top early career researchers to foster creativity and collaborations surrounding challenges in all areas of robotics." (33.7% acceptance rate)

EDUCATION

Cornell University, Ithaca, NY

August 2015 – December 2021

Ph.D. in Computer Science. Advisor: Hadas Kress-Gazit.

Cornell University, Ithaca, NY

August 2015 - June 2019

MS in Computer Science. Advisor: Ross A. Knepper.

University of Virginia, Charlottesville, VA

August 2012 – May 2015

BS (with high distinction) in Computer Science and Mathematics

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

CS 4750 (Foundations of Robotics)

Cornell University, Fall 2016 & Fall 2017

Graduate TA (syllabus creation, coding project creation and implementation, grading, office hours, occasional lecturing). Senior and graduate-level elective.

CS 1110 (Introduction to Computing Using Python)

Cornell University, Fall 2015

Head graduate TA (coordinating staff, giving review lectures, supervising lab sessions, grading, office hours). Introductory undergraduate CS course.

ENG 1501 (Introduction to Aerial Robotics)

University of Virginia, Fall 2014

Instructor. Designed and taught 1-credit special-topics undergraduate elective introducing core topics in robotics. Students built and programmed their own quadrotor robots and learned about basic kinematics, control, and perception.

CS 4610 (Programming Languages)

University of Virginia, Spring 2015

Undergraduate TA. Senior-level elective.

CS 4710 (Artificial Intelligence)

University of Virginia, Spring 2015

Undergraduate TA. Senior-level elective.

CS 4414 (Operating Systems)

University of Virginia, Spring 2014

Undergraduate TA (office hours, assignment creation). Senior-level core course.

CS 2150 (Program and Data Representation) University of Virginia, (Fall 2013 – Spring 2015). Undergraduate TA (office hours, lab supervision, grading). Sophomore-level core course.

OUTREACH

Reviewer for Black in AI: Reviewed abstracts for BAI workshop.

2017 - 2021

Mentor for Black in AI: Advised mentee on Ph.D. application process.

2019-2020

Expanding Your Horizons: Workshop Organizer/Leader.

Spring 2016, 2017, 2018

UVa HS Programming Contest: Organizer/volunteer.

Spring 2014, 2015

UVa CS Education Week Ran intro CS workshop.

Winter 2014, 2015

SERVICE

Faculty chair: RSS Pioneers 2021 workshop.

Reviewer: ICRA (2016, 2019–2021), IROS (2019, 2021), RSS (2019), WAFR (2018), MRS (2019), RO-MAN (2016), RA-L (2021), IJCAI (2021), AURO, T-ASE (2020), and SIMPAR (2018). **Departmental Service:** Student representative to Diversity and Inclusion Committee (2020–2021), Colloquim Czar (2016–2020), Administrative Colloquium Czar (2016–2019), Ph.D. Mentor Czar (2016–2018).

Professional Experience Graduate Research Assistant

January 2020 - December 2021

VRRG, Department of Computer Science, Cornell University.

Graduate Research Assistant

August 2015 - December 2019

Robotic Personal Assistants Lab, Department of Computer Science, Cornell University.

Software Engineering Intern

May 2015 - August 2015

Fluencia, Alexandria, VA. Worked on adding voice recognition for speech practice exercises.

Undergraduate Research Assistant

August 2014 - July 2015

Department of Computer Science, The University of Virginia. Work with Professor Westley Weimer on automatic software functionality transplantation.

Software Development Engineer Intern

May 2014 - August 2014

Accounts Client Team, Microsoft, Redmond, WA. Implemented cryptographic operations and network protocol for passwordless login feature in Microsoft Accounts Android app.

Software Development Engineer Intern

May 2013 - August 2013

Xbox LIVE Cloud Security Team, Microsoft, Redmond, WA. Designed and implemented a service for real-time logging and auditing of security records in Xbox LIVE. Initiated and completed a rewrite of an internal library to improve performance and provide a better API.

Undergraduate Research Assistant

January 2013 - May 2014

Department of Computer Science, The University of Virginia. Work with Professor Gabriel Robins on real-time localization of objects using passive RFID tags.

TECHNICAL SKILLS Programming Languages: Python, C++, Julia, Rust, Lua, C, Haskell, OCaml, etc.

Technologies: Linux, ROS, OMPL, Jax, PyTorch, Git, CUDA, etc.